I'll get it!
任せろ
I heard Nakao was hit by a boat.
中尾くん ボートに轢かれたって
Then, it's a lie that people won't die
if they leave Yomiyama!
夜見山の外なら死なないって嘘
Yeah, I guess.
なのかな
So, we have nowhere to run?
もう 逃げ場なし
What should we do?
どうすればいいの
Hey, should we still go on the class trip?
あのさ
合宿どうする
No way!
行くわけないじゃない
It makes no sense to go on a class trip in
the summer of a year when it happens.
「ある年」の夏休みに合宿とか
意味分かんない
It would be safest to stay locked up at home.
家に閉じこもってるのが一番安全だって
Maybe...
なのかな
Why is this even happening to us?
でもさあ
何でこんな目に遭わなきゃいけないわけ
It's so unfair.
ほんと理不尽
Yeah.
If only that transfer student
hadn't spoken to Misaki...
大体さあ あの転校生が見崎さんに話しかけたりしなかったら
But I...
俺が
I protected them.
俺が守ったのに
I left it for them...
俺が残したのに
in the classroom.
教室に
Open the eyelid that conceals the night
夜ヲ覆ウ目蓋開ケ
凶キ影ヲ恐レルナカレ
And fear not the evil shadows
I am as a doll
仄くらき柩から
Born from a dusky coffin
産み堕とされた人形のように
With a growing body frozen red
躰は赤く凍え
And a heart soothed by darkness
心は闇にあやされ育つ
Can you see me?
君に僕が見えるかい
My nails steeped in fresh blood
つなぐ手の冷たさに
Sink into the chill of our joined hands
鮮血の爪立てる
Now, let me see you frown
眉寄せてごらんよ
壊し合おう先に続く 謎に満ちる結末を
Let us destroy one another
And face the ending full of mystery that lies ahead
Before we rot away in emptiness
羽も脚ももがれたまま
With our wings and legs ripped away
虚空のなか朽ち果てるより
There is another me
もうひとり僕がいて
Who loves someone so much it hurts
誰かを痛いほど愛しているんだ
I wonder, which one is the illusion?
さぁどっちが幻だろうね
You girls be careful.
それじゃあ あなたたちも気をつけて
We will.
はい
How did Nakao seem that day?
中尾くんの当日の様子はどうだったのかな
He had a bad case of car sickness
車酔いがひどくて
and threw up a lot.
何度も吐いてましたね
Anything else?
ほかには
Well...
そうですね
He couldn't swim straight.
まっすぐ泳げてなかった
I see...
おお そうか
Maybe that's what happened!
やはりそういうことなのか
What do you mean?
どういうことです
I spoke with Mr. Ohba,
あいやね
大庭くん
a city police detective, about what happened.
夜見山署の刑事に少し話を聞いてみたんだが
And he had a nagging suspicion...
どうも死因がね
that Nakao may have been dead
before the boat hit him.
実はボートに轢かれる前に死んでたんじゃない かと
The condition of his head when he died
was inconsistent with the timing
ボートと衝突した頭部の状態だがね
of his collision with the boat.
時間が合わないらしいんだよ
The herniation caused by a cerebral contusion
had already progressed significantly.
脳挫傷による脳ヘルニアがかなり進行していたらしい
You mean, before he went to the beach?
海に来る前からってことですか
According to his family,
中尾くんの家族によれば
あの日の朝 階段から大きな音が聞こえたそうだ
they heard a loud noise from
the stairway that morning.
When they went to check it out,
様子を見に行ったものの
all they saw was Nakao hurrying out the door.
慌てて出て行く中尾くんの背中しか見られなかったという
He must have hit his head then.
その時に頭を打ってた
Most likely.
おそらく
So, the event that led to his death
took place in Yomiyama?
それって
「死」に引き込まれたのは夜見山の中だったってことですか
A safe assumption.
そう言っても問題はなかろう
When he left Yomiyama without having
his head checked at the hospital,
頭を打った状態で病院に行かず
夜見山を出てしまった時点で
his death was assured.
「死」は確定したんだ
Hey, Misaki?
あのさ 見崎
Yes?
何
Never mind.
いや いいや
I'll say it after I find out for sure.
ちゃんと分かったら言うよ
All right.
そう
Did you find that class photo
from twenty-six years ago?
二十六年前の集合写真って 見つかった
Not yet.
まだ
It's your fault.
あなたのせいよ
きみのせいだね
It's your fault.
きみのせいです
きみのせいね
It's your fault!
お前のせいだ
Inoya
The classroom?!
教室
Seriously?
それ 本当なのか
That's what Mr. Matsunaga said.
そう言ったんだよ 松永さんが
He must mean the Class 3 homeroom
in the old school building.
教室って
旧校舎の昔の三年三組だよね
But what did he hide there?
で 教室に何を隠したって
All right, well, at least we've got the location.
そっか
まっ 場所が分かっただけでも上出来だな
よし
I'll just...
Wait!
待って
I don't want to tell anyone else.
ほかの人には教えたくないんだ
Why not?
何でよ
If Nakao hadn't gone to the beach,
中尾くんさ 海に来なきゃ死ななかったと思うんだ
he probably wouldn't have died.
Still...
そりゃあ
I don't want to get anyone else involved.
だからさあ 人を増やしたくないんだ
I don't want anyone else to die.
これ以上人死にを出したくないんだよ
We shouldn't tell Akazawa or
the countermeasures committee just yet.
赤沢さんたち対策係にも
まだ言わなくていいと思う
If we find something,
何かが見つかって
and if we need their help at that point,
then we can.
それで 彼女らの協力が必要だって分かったらで
Makes sense.
ま そうだな
I wouldn't want to see Akazawa die.
赤沢が死ぬとこなんか見たくねえしな
So, when should we go to the old building?
それで いつ行く 旧校舎
We can't go right now?
これからじゃねえの
I have plans with my family this evening.
夕方から家族で出かけないと
Tomorrow would work.
明日なら
Then, how about first thing in the morning?
じゃあ 明日の早朝とかどう
Come on, anything but morning!
朝は勘弁してくれ
All right then, noon?
じゃあ 昼
A lot of club members will be around then.
昼は 部活の人が多いから
And since the second floor is barricaded...
一応旧校舎の二階って立ち入り禁止だし
Then, evening?
じゃあ 夜
Hard to look for stuff at night.
夜に探しもんすんのもな
Fine, 3 o'clock it is.
じゃあ 午後三時で決まりね
Okay.
OK
Works for me.
Okay.
いいよ
Mochizuki, the art club meets
in that building, right?
望月 美術部って 旧校舎だよな
Yeah.
そうだけど
Do any club members come in
over summer break?
夏休みって部員来るか
No, never.
誰も来ないね
Then we can meet in the club room?
じゃ 部室に集合でいいよな
Sure!
そうだね
I have a key,
鍵は持ってるし
and no one would question me being there.
僕なら旧校舎に行っても怪しくないし
Teshigawara, please don't show up
dressed like that.
勅使河原 お前 そのカッコで来るなよ
Huh? Why not?
えっ 何で
You'll stand out.
目立つって
Inoya
That's the price of being fashionable!
お洒落さんは目だっちゃおうか
Hey, do I spy Kouichi and Teshy?
恒一ちゃんとテッシ
What's the go-home club's ace
doing at school?
帰宅部のエースがなんで学校来てんの
Nothing special.
ちょっとね
We're meeting up with Mochizuki.
望月と待ち合わせでよ
ていうか 二人とも部活
You two here for club stuff?
Um...
We wanted to see Mr. Chibiki
about something.
ちょっと千曳先生にね
In the auxiliary library?
第二図書室に
Not for that.
そっちじゃなくて
Mr. Chibiki is the drama club's advisor.
千曳先生は演劇部の顧問なの
No way!
マジ
The guy who wears nothing but black?
あの黒ずくめが
That's surprising.
意外だ
He actually gives pretty solid acting advice.
あれで結構 演技指導上手いんだよね
And he looks sort of cool when he's acting.
演戯してると何気にカッコよく見えるから不思議
It's fascinating.
So?
Why exactly are you here?
二人は何しに来たの
We're looking for a clue to
stopping the calamity.
災厄を止める手掛かりを探しに来たんだ
We don't know what it is,
そりがどういうものか分からないけど
but if we do find it, we intend to
tell everyone else about it.
見つかったら ちゃんと皆に話すつもりだから
Seriously?
えっ マジ
Something like that exists?
そんなのあるんだ
できれば 自分たちの手で
We want to stop the Class 3
calamity ourselves, if we can.
三組の災厄を止めたいんだ
You guys wanna come along?
綾野と小椋も来るか
Hey!
ちょっと
I'll pass.
パス
Me too.
あたしもちょっと
Goodbye, Kouichi.
さよなら 恒一ちゃん
Later.
じゃね
さよなら
Bye.
Misaki!
見崎
Where's Mochizuki?
望月は
I don't know.
さあ
I just got here.
私もさっき来たばかりだから
Why are you here?
どうしてここに
I had nothing to do,
どこにやることもなかったし
and I didn't want to stay at home,
家にいてもね
so I thought I'd come in and draw.
絵でも描こうかと思ったんだけど
Oh...
そう
What about you?
あなたたちは
And Mochizuki's coming, too?
それに 望月くんもか
What brings you three here?
三人で何を
Well...
それは
I guess you could call it...
まあ なんつうか
exploring?
探険
Sorry I'm late!
ごめんごめん
And where do you plan to explore?
三人でどこを探険するの
Uh...
それは
Well, Teshigawara said
we should meet up here...
えっと 勅使河原くんがここに集合しようって
No, I...
いや 俺はな
Um, that's it!
あれだ
Sakaki said he had to look for something!
サカキが探しものするって言うからな
It's sort of important.
その 大事なものをね
Do Not Enter
Look, we don't know what might happen,
あのさ
Do Not Enter
何が起こるか分からないから
so I'd rather you stayed in the club room.
できれば部室にいて欲しいんだけど
I'll be fine.
私は大丈夫
Are you sure?
大丈夫って
You really are weird, Misaki.
やっぱ見崎 お前変わってんな
Aren't you scared?
怖くねえの
No, I don't think so.
たぶん 怖くない
Which room was Class 3's?
どこが三組だったんだろ
Probably the one in the middle.
真ん中じゃない
There are five classrooms.
教室は五つだし
そういやさ
By the way, didn't this old building
have seven mysteries of some kind?
この旧校舎は「七不思議」ってないの
知らねえ
I wouldn't know.
I don't give a rat's ass
about some urban legends.
大体俺「七不思議」の類には興味ねえし
So, you don't believe in
ghosts and curses and stuff?
じゃあ 霊とか祟りとかあんまり信じてないんだ
As if!
They're all just coincidences
or tricks of the eye.
ただの見間違いに偶然だって
ただ一つ うちらの「災厄」を除いてな
Except the calamity, of course.
Isn't "the secret of the auxiliary library"
one of the seven mysteries?
旧校舎の「七不思議」は
第二図書室の秘密ってやつだね
The library?
あそこが
They say you can occasionally hear
moaning coming from it.
時々あの部屋で人の呻き声が聞こえるって話
You ever heard it?
聞いたことある
No.
ないよ
I've heard there's an old archive
in its basement
あの図書室の地下に
containing secret writings that can't
be revealed to the public,
公にできない秘密の文書が隠された書庫があって
and that a librarian once locked
himself inside to guard them.
それを守るために
昔 そこに閉じ込められた司書がいてっていうの
So basically, that librarian is still alive,
そいつがまだ地下で生きていて
and you can hear him moaning
from the basement?
その声が聞こえてくるって
Bet it would just turn out to be Chibiki.
その正体は千曳っていう先生だったって落ちだろう どうせ
I hear moaning in there, sometimes.
偶に聞こえるよ
Are you serious?
マジ
Really?
ホント
Just kidding.
嘘
少し空気入れ替えましょ
Let's let in some fresh air.
You are not fine at all.
全然大丈夫じゃないじゃん
ほら 大丈夫
Yes, I am. See?
You look fine to me.
大丈夫そうだな
I wouldn't want anyone to see us
誰かに見られて
and make us into another one
of the seven mysteries.
新しい「七不思議」になるのも気が引けるし
Let's keep the windows closed.
窓は開けないでおこうよ
勅使河原
Teshigawara!
Gimme a break...
勘弁してくれよ
You seem fine.
大丈夫そうね
Take care.
元気でね
Yeah.
I'll call you.
電話するから
Later.
またね
ないね
I'm not finding anything.
I don't think it will be in a place where
it's easy to find, like in a desk.
机の中みたいな 分かりやすい場所じゃないと思う
But surely it wouldn't be
where no one could find it.
でも絶対に見つからないような場所じゃ
Then there'd be no point in leaving it.
残す意味はないし
That's true.
そうだね
It's probably not on the floor, or in any desks.
床や壁の中ってことはないと思う
What about in there?
あそこは
All I see are cleaning supplies.
掃除用具だけ かな
What's that?
何だ
Find something?
何かあったか
What's that?
何だこれ
Something's written on it.
何か書いてあるね
Let's see...
ええと
"To the future students"
将来このクラスで理不尽な災いに苦しめられるであろう後輩たちに
"who are undoubtedly suffering from the
senseless disaster of this class."
Bingo!
ビンゴ
This is it!
これだね
Mr. Matsunaga must have written that!
きっとこれも松永さんが書いたんだよ
A/V Room
I'm sure there's one in here,
but is it okay to use it?
そりゃあ ここにはあるだろうけど
いいの
As long as no one finds out.
バレなきゃ問題ないって
I found it!
あったよ
Okay, let's play it.
よし かけるぞ
Um...
ええと
My...
俺の 俺の名前は松永克巳
My name is Katsumi Matsunaga.
I'm a student of the 9th grade, Class 3 of 1983.
1983年度の三年三組の生徒で
When I finish recording this,
I plan to hide it somewhere in the classroom.
録音が終わったら このテープは教室のどこかに隠すつもりだ
If you're listening to this tape,
今このテープを聞いている「君」
you're most likely in Class 3, as well.
もしかしたら「君たち」かもしれないが
君たちが未来の三年三組の生徒
I wonder what the likelihood of that is?
その可能性はどのぐらいかな
AYANO
It's possible that you guys are also terrified
そして 君たちが 今年俺が
AYANO
俺たちが経験したのと同じような
by the senseless disaster that I... that we...
理不尽な災いに怯えている可能性は
Never mind.
まあいい
I have two reasons for leaving this tape.
俺はこんなテープを残そうと決めたのには
二つの意味があるんだ
One is to confess a sin, my sin.
一つは俺の 俺自身の罪の告白
I want to tell someone what I did.
誰かに俺がやったことを話したくて
I need someone to listen.
聞いてほしくて
The other is to give you some advice.
もう一つの意味は 後輩である君たちにアドバイスを伝えたい
It's about the extra student
who gets mixed up in the class,
クラスに紛れ込む「もう一人」と
and the calamity that happens as a result.
そいつのせいで起こる「災厄」
How it can be stopped.
これを終わらせるには どうするか
In other words...
つまり それ
Actually, I should start at the beginning.
いや やっぱり順追って話したほうがいいな
Our class went on a trip.
合宿があったんだ
We all left on August 8,
for three days and two nights.
八月八日から
二泊三日でクラス合宿が
Our homeroom teacher, Mr. Koga,
had suggested that we visit a local shrine.
担任の古賀先生が言い出したんだ
合宿をして 神社にお参りをしようって
There's an old shrine in this town
called Yomiyama Shrine.
夜見山には 「夜見山神社」っていう古い神社があるんだ
そこに 皆でお参りをしたら
He said that if we all prayed there,
he was sure the curse would be lifted.
きっと呪いが消えるに違いないって
There were twenty-two students in all,
myself included.
参加した生徒は 俺を含めて二十人
We only half believed him.
皆 半信半疑だったけど
On the second day,
合宿二日目
we climbed the mountain to visit the shrine.
その日 俺たちは先生と山に登って
神社にお参りしたんだ
It was so old and run-down,
ひどく寂れた神社だった
like it had been abandoned by the world.
何だか もう世界から見捨てられちまってるような
この町の名前がついた神社だってのに
Even though it bears the name of the city,
it looked like it hadn't been maintained at all.
全然管理されてない感じだった
So, we decided to clean up
the grounds while we were there.
だから お参りついでに皆で境内を掃除して
At the time, we hoped that maybe
this would lift the curse.
あの時は 「もしかしたら これで呪いが解けるんじゃないか」
みたいな気分になったんだけど
And after we prayed,
our teacher confidently declared,
お参りの後 先生は自信たっぷりに
"Everything will be all right now."
「これでもう大丈夫です」って
But it wasn't.
ところが ダメだったんだ
It wasn't that easy.
そんな甘いもんじゃなかった
As soon as we left the shrine,
神社の帰り道でさっそくだった
the clear skies suddenly turned overcast,
ずっといい天気だったのが
いきなり雲行きが怪しくなってきて
and it began to rain,
雨が降り出して
complete with lightning strikes.
しかも ひどい雷雨でさ
As we hurried down the mountain,
慌てて山を下る中
the first victim was a boy named Hamaguchi.
最初にやられたのは 浜口っていう男子だった
He was kind of dumb.
バカなやつでさ
He was the only one
who'd brought an umbrella.
用意周到に傘なんか持って来てて
一人さしてたんだ
And we were on a mountain,
in a lightning storm...
山道で雷雨だってのに
He was walking in front of me, when...
その浜口が俺の前を歩いてたんだが
For a second, my vision went white,
一瞬視界が 真っ白になってさ
and I heard a huge crash.
同時に凄い音がしたんだ
Hamaguchi had been struck by lightning.
浜口に雷が落ちたんだ
I still remember the smell
of his flesh burning...
肉が焦げる嫌な匂いを 今でも覚えてる
Anyway, the students panicked and bolted,
それでもう その場はパニックさ
leaving Hamaguchi behind,
浜口のことは放ったらかして
desperate to get off the mountain
as quickly as possible.
ほとんどの生徒が走り出して
とにかく早く山を下りなきゃって
雨の中を闇雲に走り出したすぐ後だった
But moments after we all took off,
blindly running through the rain...
二人目の犠牲者が出たんだ
The second victim was taken.
A girl named Hoshikawa.
星川って女子だった
パニクって走るうちに 足を踏み外して 崖から落ちちまって
In her panic,
she slipped and fell off a tall, sheer cliff.
切り立った高い崖で
All we could do was call for help
at the foot of the mountain.
下山して助けを呼ぶしかなかったんだ
But in the end, we couldn't
save either of them.
結局 二人とも助からなかった
Praying at the shrine had
no effect whatsoever.
神社のお参りなんて 何の効果もなかった
Now, this is the important part.
肝心なのは この後だ
Right after we finally reached
the bottom of the mountain,
やっとの思いで下山した直後
that's when it happened.
それがあったんだ
And by it, I mean...
それっていうのは つまり
I...
俺が
Damn!
ヤベッ
That was close.
危ねえ
I was in a cold sweat.
さすがに冷や汗が出たよ
Yeah, same.
まったくだよ
The tape!
テープ
ちょっと
Oh, no.
Idiot.
バカめ
You've gotta be kidding!
マジかよ
We didn't get to hear the important part!
肝心なとこ聞いてないんだけど
What should we do?!
どうすんだよ
All we need to do is fix the tape.
修理したら きっと聞けるよ
It can be fixed?!
これ直せるのか
I think it's possible.
できなくはないと思うけど
Great! Thanks, buddy!
よし じゃあ 任せた
We've gotta hear the rest!
続き 聞かせろよな
Do you mind if we leave it with you?
任せられて 大丈夫
うん とにかく やってみるよ
I'll give it my best shot.
Brother!
兄貴
Like film that loses its color with time
色褪せてく フィルムのように
The now that we know will one day fade
確かな今も いずれ霞んで
That fleeting moment's light
何でもなく 笑いあった
When we shared a laugh over nothing
刹那の時間と光
It now lies, waiting to be found, at the depths
繋がってゆく 記憶の底に
Of memories that connect one to the next
誰かが見つけるためあると信じてる 今でも
This I still believe
"Glass eye"